Guide to the Eugene Lerner Josephine Baker collection, 1926-2001
Department of Special Collections
Lerner, Eugene, collector. The Josephine Baker collection,
1926-2001
M1297
Lerner, Eugene, collector.
3 linear ft. (6 manuscript boxes, 1 map folder)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
African American Paris stage performer noted for her comic, yet sensual, dance routines. While she took Europe by storm, racism in her native United States prevented her from being wholly accepted until 1973, just two years before her death. The material was collected by Gene Lerner. The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, audio tapes, clippings, and publications.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 2002.
Biography
African American Paris stage performer noted for her comic, yet sensual, dance routines. While she took Europe by storm, racism in her native United States prevented her from being wholly accepted until 1973, just two years before her death. The material was collected by Gene Lerner.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, audio tapes, clippings, and publications gathered by her authorized biographer, Eugene Lerner, as part of his efforts to document her life. Includes original letters in the hand of Josephine Baker and the people in her life, including Pepito Abatino, Maria Li Bassi Abatino, Jo Bouillon, Princess Grace of Monaco, Hank Kaufman, Richard A. Martin, Jr., Madam d' Ora, Diana Ross, Christina Abatino Scoto, Milton J. Shapp, Margarette Wallace, Rama Wallace, Walter Winchell.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Abatino, Pepito.; Abatino, Maria Li Bassi.; Bouillon, Jo, 1908-; Grace, Princess of Monaco, 1929-1982.; Kaufman, Hank.; Lerner, Eugene, collector.; Martin, Richard A., Jr.; Ora, Madam d', 1881-1963.; Ross, Diana.; Scoto, Christina Abatino.; Shapp, Milton J., 1912-; Wallace, Margarette.; Wallace, Rama.; Winchell, Walter, 1897-1972.; The Stork Club (New York, N.Y.); The Bobino.; Ziegfeld Follies.; African American dancers.; Phonotapes.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Resume of the contents of Gene Lerner archive on Josephine Baker [1 of 2]2001, File A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Includes A. Introduction; B. Her itinerary through life; C. The individual indexes of materials included in the archives
- Resume of the contents of Gene Lerner archive on Josephine Baker [2 of 2]2001, File A (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Josephine with Kaufman & Lerner1973-1975, File no. 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Kaufman, Hank; Lerner, Gene
- Letters of Pepito Abatino1926-1934, File no. 2 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Abatino, Pepito
- Letters of Maria Li Bassi Mule Abatino (mother of Pepito) to her daughter Christina Scoto from Paris, Berlin, Rome1927-1929, File no. 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Abatino, Maria Li Bassi; Scoto, Christina
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [1 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Scoto, Christina Abatino
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [2 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Contains correspondence, 1930 1939
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [3 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Contains correspondence, 1940 1949
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [4 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [5 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Contains correspondence, 1950 1959
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [6 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [7 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [8 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Josephine's letters to Christina Abatino Scoto (including a limited number of letters to and from others) [9 of 9]1929-1963, File no. 4 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Contains correspondence, 1960 1963
- Correspondence, Jo Bouillon and his family1951-1979, File no. 5 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Bouillon, Jo
- Margarette and Rama Wallace (Josephine's sister and niece) correspondence with Kaufman and Lerner1976-1988, File no. 6 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Wallace, Margarette; Wallace, Rama; Lerner, Gene; Kaufman, Hank
- Correspondence of Richard A. Martin, Jr., Josephine's nephew1975-1978, File no. 7 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Martin, Richard A., Jr.; Oberhellmann, Elmer C.
- Correspondence, Captain Jacques Abtey1975-1976, File no. 8 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Abtey, Jacques, Captain.
- Princess Grace of Monaco, correspondence re. Josephine1971-1990, File no. 9 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Grace, Princess of Monaco, 1929-1982; Marouani, Felix; Cohen, Rob; Levy-Soussan, Louisette; Kaufman, Hank; Lerner, Gene; Brialy, Jean-Claude; Choisit, Paul; Rainier III, Prince of Monaco, 1923-
- Diana Ross, correspondence with and about1975-1984, File no. 10 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Kaufman, Hank; Bouillon, Jo; Ross, Diana; Lerner, Gene; Montgomery, Robert H., Jr.
- General correspondence about Josephine1975-1990, File no. 11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Lerner, Gene; Daniel, Clifton; Kirkpatrick, Scott; Dixon, Florence; Kaufman, Hank; Buchanan, Bessie; Shapp, Milton J., 1912-; Vardi, Yaffa; Jessye, Eva; Hurford Janes, Henry
- Sous-Lieutenant Josephine Baker; Lerner and Kaufman correspondence with French government and army [1 of 2]1944-1977, File no. 12 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Sous-Lieutenant Josephine Baker; Lerner and Kaufman correspondence with French government and army [2 of 2]1944-1977, File no. 12 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- FBI, U.S. Army Intelligence, National Security Agency, United States Department of State correspondence and File No. 62-98534, Federal Bureau investigation on Josephine Baker, file containing 258 pages [1 of 3]1986-1988, File no. 13 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; Central Intelligence Agency; FBI; CIA
- FBI, U.S. Army Intelligence, National Security Agency, United States Department of State correspondence and File No. 62-98534, Federal Bureau investigation on Josephine Baker, file containing 258 pages [2 of 3]1986-1988, File no. 13 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- FBI, U.S. Army Intelligence, National Security Agency, United States Department of State correspondence and File No. 62-98534, Federal Bureau investigation on Josephine Baker, file containing 258 pages [3 of 3]1986-1988, File no. 13 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Planned trip to the United States of Jo Bouillon and the twelve Baker-Bouillon children1975-1976, File no. 14 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Josephine's engagements, excluding the Ziegfeld Follies of 1936, Carnegie Hall of 1973, and Josephine at the Babino, 1975.1933-1974, File no. 15 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- The Ziegfeld Follies of 1936.1935-1936, and 1987, File no. 16 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Ziegfeld Follies
- Josephine Baker at Carnegie Hall1973, File no. 17 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Carnegie Hall
- Josephine at The Babino, Paris, 1975.1974-1975, File no. 18 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  The Babino
- The battle with the Stork Club and Walter Winchell, 19511951-1960, File no. 19 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Winchell, Walter; The Stork Club
- Save Les Milandes1965, File no. 20 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Les Milandes
- American Women of Style (exhibit), The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1975-1976, File no. 21; Includes photographs (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York; The Costume Institute
- Release of Josephine's 1930s French films in the United States1989, File no. 22 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- TV and theatre productions about Josephine's life [1 of 2]1986-1991, File no. 23 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- TV and theatre productions about Josephine's life [2 of 2]1986-1991, File no. 23 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Items and reviews of books published after death1976-2001, File no. 24 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Papich, Stephen; Hammond, Byran; O'Connor, Patrick; Rose, Phyllis; Baker, Jean-Claude; Chase, Chris; Wood, Ean; Haney, Lynn
- Articles and interviews [1 of 2]1927-1992, File no. 25 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Articles and interviews [2 of 2]1927-1992, File no. 25 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Press, publicity, memoranda on Kaufman & Lerner production plans for the life story1975-1989, File no. 27 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Books and excerpts of books re Josephine [1 of 2]1928-1976, File no. 29 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Le memorie di Josephine Baker / by Marcel Sauvage (Italian ed., 1928) -- Les memoires di Josephine Baker / by Marcel Sauvage (2nd French ed., 1945)
  Sauvage, Marcel; Piceni, Enrico; Kaufman, Hank; Lerner, Gene; Abatino, P.; La Camara, Felix, 1897-
- Books and excerpts of books re Josephine [2 of 2]1928-1976, File no. 29 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Il mio amico Charlot / by Enrico Piceni -- Hollywood on the Tiber / by Hank Kaufman & Eugene Lerner -- Mon sang dans tes veines / Felix La Camara and P. Abatino
- Photographs (9 prints)1926-1973, File no. 31 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Josephine Baker; Ora, Madam d', 1881-1963; Abatino, Pepito; Magnani, Anna; Karsten, Eddie
- Obituaries and tributes1975-1982, File no. 33 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Variety Club Foundation tribute to Josephine, Metropolitan Opera House, New York1976, File no. 34 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Variety Club Foundation; Metropolitan Opera House, New York
- Chez Josephine: exhibition, Taormina (catalog and 2 articles)1987, File no. 35 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Mollica, Vincenzo; Fellini, Federico
- Miscellaneous (7 items)1927-2001, File no. 37 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Some Gene Lerner writings [1 of 3]1976-1989, File no. 38 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Contains Journey toward Josephine, January 25 to February 7th, 1977 / by Eugene Lerner
- Some Gene Lerner writings [2 of 3]1976-1989, File no. 38 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Contains Josephine: the life story of Josephine Baker / by Eugene Lerner
- Some Gene Lerner writings [3 of 3]1976-1989, File no. 38 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Contains My Sweetheart my life / by Eugene Lerner
- Documents re exclusive world-wide rights to the life story of Josephine Baker1975-1979, File no. 26 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Lerner, Gene; Kaufman, Hank
- Sheet music of Josephine Baker songs plus Score of La Creole [1 of 2]1930-1968, nd, File no. 28; (21 items) (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Sheet music of Josephine Baker songs plus Score of La Creole [2 of 2]1930-1968, nd, File no. 28; (21 items) (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Josephine in magazines and the Congressional Record [1 of 3]1928-1976, File no. 32 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Chateauneu, Roger; Vreeland, Diana; Berenson, Marisa; Chase, Barbara
- Miscellaneous brochures, flyers, catalogs (6 items)1950-2000 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Josephine in magazines and the Congressional Record [2 of 3]1928-1976, File no. 32 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Josephine in magazines and the Congressional Record [3 of 3]1928-1976, File no. 32 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Tapes of and about Josephine (3 reel to reel, 5 casette)1970-1976, nd, File no. 30 (Box 7)
- Josephine a Bobino (record album cover)1975 (Map-case [Location pending])
  Bobino